Ruth Dietrich Tuttle Papers, 1889-1984
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Ruth Dietrich Tuttle papers
1889-1984
1920-1923
Tuttle, Ruth Dietrich, 1887-1984
MS 236
2 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author, pacifist, and feminist. The Tuttle papers include writings, including an unpublished autobiography; photographs; speeches; research material; and records from Tuttle's involvement with various peace organizations. Topics covered include peace, internationalism, birth control rights, suffrage, women's clubs, and women writers. Correspondents include Virginia Gildersleeve, Florence Lamont, Anna Garlin Spencer, and Portia Willis (Berg) Fitzgerald.
1887 Born, Harrisburg, PA, 17 June
1909 Graduated from Smith College
1913 Married Melsom S. Tuttle
1915 Son, Russell Conwell, born
1920 Sailed for China, where Melsom Tuttle was assigned to do educational work for the YMCA. He became principal of the American School in Peking.
1922-1923 Taught English to Chinese boys
1923 Daughter, Carol Cathay, born
1924 Melsom Tuttle sent home because of ill health, died en route, 3 July, rest of family returned to the U.S.
1940- Social worker at Hartford Retreat and Flower Hospital in New York City
1952 Moved to Northampton, MA
1984 Died, Concord, MA, 27 May
The Ruth Dietrich Tuttle Papers consist of eight linear inches of correspondence, printed material, diaries, memorabilia, and photographs. The major portion of the material dates from the Tuttle's service in China from 1920-23, although there is also material relating to Ruth's life before her marriage.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Correspondence
II. Biography and Memorabilia
III. Diaries
IV. Photographs
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any added restrictions.
History of the Collection
Ruth Dietrich Tuttle donated her photograph album with other Smith College items in October 1971. The bulk of the Papers was the gift of her daughter, Carol Tuttle Christian, in May 1990. Carol Christian and her brother, Russell Conwell Tuttle donated the 1906-1909 diaries and additional photographs in October 1997.
Search Terms
Missionaries--China--History--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Tuttle, Melsom S.; Tuttle, Ruth Dietrich, 1887-1984; China--Description and travel--Sources; China--Social life and customs--1912-1937--Sources
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  This series contains two sections: Ruth D. Tuttle and Melsom S. Tuttle. The first consists primarily of letters that Ruth wrote home to her parents between 1920 and 1923. These are substantive letters describing her life in Peking, her teaching experiences, and Chinese customs. they reflect the social live of foreign missionaries living in a homogenous community overseas. There are also letters to her from Melsom, 1913-22, and from many of the Chinese students she taught, 1922-27, and a few miscellaneous letters. The second section contains a smaller amount of correspondence from Melsom to his family consisting mostly of postcards, 1920-22, and several miscellaneous letters to him, 1923.
- SERIES II. BIOGRAPHY AND MEMORABILIA
  This series consists of clippings and other printed material; and notes and lists that belonged to Ruth Tuttle. There are also compositions written by Chinese students and miscellaneous China memorabilia.
- SERIES III. DIARIES
  This series consists entirely of Ruth's diaries, 1906-1909 and 1918. The four volumes from 1906-1909 are a fairly complete record of her Smith years. She faithfully made daily entries, at minimum recording the day's activities, and often reflecting on the days events and relationships with friends and classmates. The one volume five-year diary appears to encompass the years from 1918 to 1922. Melsom Tuttle's name is written in the volume, and a few of the entries appear to be his, but most are in Ruth's hand.
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS
  This series consists of twenty-one personal and family photographs, 1889, 1920-23; two of the prisoner-of-war camp in Vernon, British Columbia, 1919, where Melsom Tuttle directed YMCA activities; thirty miscellaneous snapshots of China, 1920-23; a photo album, 1907-1915 (including Smith College photos); and an undated oversized photograph of Ruth Tuttle and a class of Chinese students.
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Ruth D. Tuttle
    - Outgoing to family, 1915-25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Incoming
      - Melsom Tuttle, 1913-22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Students, 1922-27 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1912-24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Melsom S. Tuttle
    - Outgoing to family, 1920-22, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous incoming, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- SERIES II. BIOGRAPHY AND MEMORABILIA
  - Clippings, lists, and notes, 1924-84 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Compositions by Chinese students, 1922-23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1919-26, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- SERIES III. DIARIES
  - 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1908-1909, 1918-circa 1922 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Personal and family (21), 1889, 1920-1923 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Prisoner of war camp, Vernon, B.C. (2), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - China, miscellaneous (30), 1920-23 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Album (including Smith College), 1907-15 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Ruth Tuttle with Chinese students, undated